This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Hello everyone. This is Felina for SE
Radio. I'm here today with Zachary Burt.
Zachary was born in Palo Alto in 1987
and since 2002 he's been working both as
an individual contributor and in
leadership roles. In 2007 he sold his
PHP application lame factor to WikiHow
and launched a software consultancy
business. He's passionate about open
source both in submitting pull requests
and launching open source projects.
Welcome to the show Zach.
Hi Felina. I am super excited to be here
and thank you.
Cool, let's go then. I think that most
people know what freelancing is, they
have an idea what it means, but could
you give your definition of freelancing?
Absolutely. So I see freelancing as
performing a la carte tasks for
uh firms. So rather than being on a
salaried employment schedule, you are uh
either paid hourly or on a per project
basis for the work that you deliver.
So this there's also a change here in
the social contract between you and the
firm.
So
in most uh western cultures there's a
social contract that when you're an
employee
the firm will take care of you to a
certain extent. Maybe they will provide
uh certain health benefits
or um perhaps coordinated through the
state they will provide certain
unemployment benefits should your
position be made redundant. But with
freelancing
there is no social contract to that
extent,
and you are just
pretty much being paid in exchange for
the work that you deliver. So, in a
normal employment job, uh there will be
some downtime, and you'll be paid for
that anyway. And if for some reason your
manager isn't active in putting you to
work, you're going to receive a paycheck
anyway.
Whereas with freelancing,
you're being paid for actively
delivering results.
Uh that answer already touches upon so
many things we will cover in the show
today. So, you mentioned benefits, you
mentioned the social contract, you
mentioned how to how to deal with
downtime, and we will talk about all of
those things later in the show. So, I'm
really happy with your definition. It's
so all-encompassing.
But, I'm also really curious about uh
your personal story. Did you always
freelance, or did you work for a boss
before?
That's a great question. Um and now, and
I don't want to be pedantic, but, you
know, when you are freelancing,
uh you do have a boss. Your bosses are
your clients.
Yeah, sure.
So,
um but,
uh my very my very first foray into the
world of professional development was as
a freelancer rather than as a full-time
employee.
I started freelancing when I was 15
years old.
I was in uh high school computer science
class, and instead of paying attention
to the lecture,
I was finding freelance work for myself.
Uh there
There was this There was this web forum
that was very popular back in the day
called the Something Awful Forums.
And I found my first client through uh
the web forums there. I didn't even
realize that uh I was being a
freelancer. Someone needed help with
something, and I
wanted to help, and then uh he paid me
afterwards.
Oh, that's cool.
that was That was
That was my start.
Um and then uh
I was very fortunate when I was 17 to
find an internship with a local software
company. And I had a boss then. It was
it was definitely like that kind of you
know employee
boss relationship. But um I we were we
were collab- it was a very collaborative
internship and
I started doing projects. I was inspired
by the work that we did together and I
started doing projects on my own
independently. And a couple years later
one of my projects took off and then
uh people started approaching me and
asked me to freelance for them. And yeah
that's when I started consulting. Now
the term freelancing and consulting
they're kind of
false equivalents.
Sometimes they're used interchangeably.
Consulting is generally a little bit of
a higher end implication. So if you're
consulting you're going to be charging
at a higher rate whether it's hourly or
daily, weekly or or project-based for a
fixed deliverable.
Um whereas freelancing has a little bit
of a
lower end implication.
But in practice they are
interchangeable.
But there there are some nuances there.
I hope that helps.
Yeah I I think if I the my personal
definition indeed is if you're a
freelancer you're maybe closer to a
programmer or developer. Whereas if
you're consulting maybe you're closer to
a manager or project lead. You're a
little bit higher in the hierarchy of
the company as well. Does that make
sense?
I would say that
yeah I would definitely agree with that
definition. When when you use the word
consultant
uh you are almost always going to be
responsible for delivering some kind of
business result.
Yeah.
Whereas with freelancing, it's more
about, say, doing a la carte tasks.
Like
one example that I use in a book is
if you told me, you know, uh you know,
update my webpage and then you tell me
exactly what to do,
and I deliver you the code, that could
be a freelance assignment. But if I tell
you, "Well, no, I'm going to update the
webpage for these reasons and it's going
to result in this change in conversion
rate or this change in user behavior."
That's closer to a consulting role.
Where I definitely see
uh consultants as
uh being more in touch with the bigger
picture of the business.
Yeah, so they're more thinking along
about business cases and customers
rather than just delivering software.
Yes, absolutely. And and required a
little bit more
self-management,
self-starting,
and uh beginning with the end in mind
rather than caught up in the technical
details.
Yeah, I see. But for the remainder of
this show, let's just use freelancer as
the word for both these type of roles,
then I don't have to say freelancer or
consultant all the time.
That sounds good to me.
Why do companies want freelancers? What
is the benefit from the company side of
having freelancers rather than full-time
employees?
Sure. So, if a company has a specific
project that they need delivered,
that they don't have the in-house
resources available to do,
then they will turn towards an external
consultant.
Like, for example, let's say you're a
manager and you have a project that you
believe is going to deliver a high ROI
or return on investment to your firm.
It's going to have a good result, but
your full-time employees are busy with
another high-priority task. I mean, it's
always the case that there's too much
work and not enough resources,
but sometimes, especially if you have a
task that's going to generate a positive
return on investment for doing,
then companies will look outside the
organization
to find a freelancer who can take care
of a specific
uh one-off task, you know, and that may
not require
uh
having deep knowledge of the company
culture or other systems.
Uh
but generally, companies will look to
find a freelancer when there are
projects that they have a very strong
confidence of having a good return on
investment.
And then, where is the threshold? Is
there an ideal percentage of
freelancers? Because the way you
describe it now is as a company, I could
also just use only freelancers for all
these tasks, and maybe only have uh
C-level employees to steer all of the
freelancers. Is that a good idea?
It's definitely a possibility, and I uh
I think that we are shifting as a global
economy increasingly towards this type
of sharing economy or gig economy
uh type of uh trading system.
So, uh
with I
That's That's my perception of the
macroeconomic trend is that we're going
to see more and more freelancing,
especially as employers are discouraged
from maintaining full-time employees
because
people want to work remotely,
and uh there may be penalties at At
least in the US, there are penalties at
state level for retaining full-time
employees. You have to pay additional
taxes.
Uh additionally, in in the US, I can
tell you that through the Bureau of
Labor Statistics, one in seven web
developers are self-employed
freelancers.
Wow, that's quite a high number. I would
I'm surprised.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely. And
I think we're going to see that percent
increasing going forward. But let's also
remember that the vast majority of web
development is WordPress. And I don't
want to insult WordPress or PHP. You
know, they're both excellent tools for
the right type of problem, but in the
more hardcore software engineering
community
people tend to sort of sneer at
WordPress and PHP as not being the most
programmer-friendly
tools due to
a number of reasons, speed, syntax
inconsistencies,
that type of thing.
But the vast majority of websites
the
number one platform for websites on the
internet is WordPress. So
there's a a long tail of websites that
need to be built.
Essentially, every business needs its
own website, and
you know, the first step right now the
the easiest thing for them to do is just
to put up a Facebook page.
But if they want their own website, then
they have to start looking at either
WordPress or tools like Wix or
Squarespace.
And while those tools are you know,
decent enough
if you want to do any level of
sophisticated customization, not even
sophisticated, but anything other than
just the basic, you know, text, images,
videos, and basic forms
you're going to need
a web developer to help customize that.
So you think in the future there's going
to be a bigger market even for more
freelancing jobs because of these
relatively small specialized tasks that
companies need to outsource.
Yeah, well, I can tell you that the
market for software developers is
unquestionably growing.
Uh the phrase in the startup community
is software is eating the world and I
don't I don't know exactly how true that
is, but I can tell you that there are
more jobs for
programmers than ever.
And I can also tell you that there's a
macroeconomic trend towards gig economy
style labor. Now, of course, a lot of
that is driven by the big players in the
market like Uber and Lyft who, you know,
have more uh independent contractors
and that is definitely shifting the
market, but uh I am seeing that there is
an increased demand for
uh freelance uh talent, you know, at at
all ends of the market and both the high
end and at the low end.
Yes, so we you talked about skills
already a little bit when you answered
the question. You said companies need
people with a specific skill. So, what
type of skills, what type of programming
or content skills do you need to be a
developer? Is there like a unique skill
or a few skills that you think are
really marketable or can it just be any
type of programming you're good at?
Uh great question. Uh so, the first
thing I'm going to say is that
if you are hungry for freelance work and
you need income ASAP,
the number one technical skill to learn
is WordPress development.
I I wish it weren't the case, honestly.
I mean, uh uh my the first programming
language that I really used seriously
independently was Pearl and uh then I
then I did move into PHP a bit and once
I moved out of PHP,
you know, I I just I realized, you know,
uh there there are other high-level
languages that are a lot nicer. But just
having PHP WordPress skills and some
JavaScript HTML CSS skills is is
definitely the kind of skill that will
put food on the table now. If you need
it now and if you need to go out and
make money today, the number one thing
you could do is have WordPress as a
skill. It is something that you can fall
back on cuz there is just such a huge
demand for WordPress work and WordPress
customizations.
I mean, when you're in when you're in a
software engineering firm or or software
engineering department, you don't think
about it cuz nobody in the snobby
developer community really talks too
much about PHP and WordPress.
But it it is the most prominent
predominant
skill required. And I have a tool that
spiders a lot of freelance listings and
I can tell you that just statistically,
the most jobs that I see require
WordPress and JavaScript as a skill.
Now, I want to make an important
distinction and say that for
freelancing,
uh something that's equally important to
having the technical skill is having the
sales skill.
So being able to build trust with a
client and get them to agree to work
with you
is just a tremendously important skill
for freelancing.
Um then there are the other, you know,
soft skills around that like getting
them to actually pay you and keeping
them as a client so you don't have to go
find new clients all the time.
But uh generally, having that sales, a
little bit of a sales soft skill, making
sure that you aren't like
insulting them by criticizing their
technical knowledge or lack thereof and
just that sort of, you know, warm
politeness,
uh
empathizing, being able to imagine what
they're feeling and speak to their
feelings.
Those are just very important skills to
have as a freelancer.
Now, that's a great answer. Actually, my
second next question was going to be
what's what soft skills do you need? And
I like your answer about the the sales
skills, but it feels to me a little bit
like the sales skills you're describing
are more important during a project than
before a project. If I think about
sales, that's like how am I going to get
customers. But what you're describing is
more about how to retain customers and
make sure that you can continue to work
for them. Is that correct? Is that the
most important part of the sales skill?
Yes, uh, communication is the most
important thing. Managing expectations
through communication.
So, being in touch, being communicating
respect
is a very important thing at sort of
like an animal level.
Uh,
making sure that you're not,
you know, communicating that, you know,
I am better than you. Do you know what I
mean?
Yeah.
being, you know, it's it's a tricky
balance balancing having the confidence
that of being an authority
without being insulting to the other
person. Like you see on four web forums
like Hacker News,
you see people just tearing each other
to their to shreds all the time.
And when you're dealing with prospective
client, you have to be very careful
about that. And uh, you know, being very
respectful of them and understanding
that
perhaps they may not be as sharp as you
technically,
but hey, they're the ones with the
business and they're the ones who would
be writing your check and you know,
paying you in the first place. So, it's
important to keep that in mind. Now,
when when I talked about this the before
you get the customer, the most important
thing is
building trust.
So, making sure that they believe what
you say and that you are the person who
can solve their problem.
And there are a variety of ways you can
do that. Um you know, one the best you
know, way to do that is to get someone
they know
to uh sing your praises.
So, that that's probably the the most
sure fire way for building trust. But,
another way to build trust is just uh
social proof.
So, for example, having a social media
account with a lot of followers. That
can be a very powerful signal.
Having a web portfolio where people can
see the results that you've delivered.
And people come to me a lot and they
say, you know, I don't have a portfolio
because
I'm a back-end developer. And I've never
built a system from scratch by myself.
So, how can I have any sort of web
presence to show off, you know, the
business logic that I wrote. You know, I
I would feel disingenuous
showing screenshots of the front end of
a website that I worked on the back end
for.
So, my answer to that is one,
it's okay to talk about the front end
and show as long as you make it very
clear that you worked on a different
aspect of the system. And the next is
you should be able to get a reference
from anyone you work with.
And
if you have them as a reference, then
you can say
I you know, I I may not have a portfolio
or you may not even need to mention a
portfolio, but
here is someone I've worked for. Here is
their contact information.
Uh you know, ask them honestly about my
performance and they will be able to
tell you.
And
getting uh anyone you work with, whether
it's an employer or a freelance client,
you should try to both ask them for a
reference. And if it's a freelance
client, also ask for referrals. So, say,
"Do you have anyone in mind who could
also benefit from my services? Right now
I'm I have the ability to take on some
new clients."
And that's a great way because getting a
referral from someone you trust in the
real world
um is one of the best uh buying signals.
Those are all great tips and I have a
few more things that you might think of
in terms of marketing that I want to
really hear your opinion on. For
example, what about speaking at
conferences? I know this is a thing that
freelancers do. Do you think that's
worth it because it takes lots of time
to travel to a conference and to prepare
a great talk?
Oh, yeah. Absolutely. It's one of the
best channels for
demonstrating that you're an authority
in the subject matter
and uh also the social proof angle that
other people find what you say to be
value enough valuable enough so that
they actually pay attention to what
you're saying.
So if you can get uh a conference
speaking gig,
that is awesome. And hopefully it'll be
recorded and you can put it up on your
website and you can put it on your CV
and you can easily have a slide during
your presentation that says,
"By the way, I do uh consulting.
Uh feel free to get in touch with me. My
info's on the website, easy to Google."
But that sort of thing. And if you have
a web presence, you definitely want to
make sure that you have a contact me
link. Uh you know, don't really worry
too much about obscuring your email from
spammers. Don't make people solve a
puzzle in order to contact you. Um you
know, there's some tricks you can do
like putting part of your email in like
a span tag to to to fool some of the
email harvesting software.
But you want to put your contact
information readily available and you
also want to make it absolutely clear
that you're available for consulting
work. Whether it's on your LinkedIn or
your web page or your social media. If
you're blogging or if you're giving
talks on conferences about technical
topics, that's a great lead gen channel
for clients who are looking for an
authority to help them and may be
interested in paying for that.
Yeah, you mentioned blogging. I want to
ask more a little about content
marketing as well. So, blogging but also
recording podcasts, things like that can
also show your authority.
But it also takes a lot of time. So, do
you think that that is worth it? Or
maybe what do you think is the best way?
Is a conference talk better than if you
blog post or a few social media posts?
Yeah, you know, um
if you can get accepted to conference
talks, give a conference talk,
absolutely. Everyone I know who does
consulting and also gives talks has so
much business.
Um in terms of blogging,
some people are going to be able to just
find you through search, but um it helps
if you also submit your content to
social media aggregators. So, it's not
just build it and they will come.
You know, write the post and then submit
it to either Hacker News or the specific
technical Reddit that you're writing
about. Uh
and uh put it on Twitter
and tweet at some people who might like
it. Getting people to discover your
content is just as important. And you
know, you mentioned book. I wrote a book
recently and I have to tell you
economically,
writing a book is not a good idea if
you're just looking to make money from
the sales of the book.
Um
you it's just it's just not a smart
proposition. You can make much better
money for your time working a minimum
wage job than you can for all the effort
it takes to write a book.
However, it becomes a very strong
credibility indicator.
So, people are going to read your book
and then contact you for services. And
then when you tell clients that you've
written a book,
it's like it's a very good signal to
them because
uh it it's sort of a time-honored way of
demonstrating credibility
or believability. So, that when you say
something, they believe it's true and
they can trust it.
So, a book works more in the way it's
not that people will see your book in a
store and they're like, "Oh, I need to
call this guy for consulting." It's more
that when you're already speaking to
people and they find out you have a
book, then that's a good way to build
the trust that you referred to earlier.
Yes, absolutely. But, if they happen to
need help with something specific that
you happen to have written a book about
and you know, they have a copy of that
book,
many times people will contact the
authors of books and ask for help.
I know I certainly have for, you know,
various
uh
programming manuals over the years
for various topics.
So, let's talk a little bit more about
going from the first contact to actually
landing the job. You've You've been in
touch with someone that you emailed you
through your book or your blog or
whatever and they're like, "Are you open
for new job?" And you are.
Then what happens? Because if you have a
regular full-time employment, you have a
job interview and probably a series of
interviews with a technical person and
maybe someone from HR. What is the
process into a freelancing gig?
There are a couple ideas that I want to
share here.
One is that
um it it pays to be persistent in
following up.
Um
I know some sales people who will follow
up with a lead
seven times before they give up on it.
So, if a lead goes dead,
you know, you can consider emailing them
once a week for 7 weeks with, you know,
a follow-up. And it's when you're
selling yourself, that's just something
that you have to be able to feel
comfortable
with following up and persisting.
Now, ideally, anytime you follow up, you
want to also add some new information.
For example, I've been thinking about
your business. Here's an interesting
article that you might
enjoy.
Or have you considered this type of
solution to your problem?
So, follow-up is definitely essential.
Now, insofar as
uh
scheduling interviews, uh a lot of
companies will if you're going to be
freelancing for a big company, then yes,
you may have to go through an interview
process.
But as long as you're transparent and
honest about your situation,
that is way better than just
uh lying about the issue and um then
being flaky in your communication.
You want to be as direct as possible
when setting expectations. You want to
know about how much time you have
available per week.
You also want to know about your
proficiency and what kind of results the
client can expect from that time period.
And a lot of clients will be flexible
about scheduling your meetings to be
respectful of your working hours. Now, a
tip that I have
uh when you're freelancing and also
working a full-time job
is that I like to do my freelancing in
the morning before I go into work.
Because that way I'm fresh. I can put in
some of my best hours there. And then I
you know, I go into the the job
and you know, a lot of being at a
full-time employee job is being having
downtime, you know. You talk to the
programmers, developers. A lot of people
will say, you know, honestly, I only do
about you know, maybe 6 hours of coding
a week. The rest is meetings, stand-up
meetings,
you know,
I just various political things they
have do, town hall meetings, all that
stuff. So, if you're if you're
freelancing and your job is just
delivering
value, um
it works very well for a lot of people
just work outside of office hours. Just
don't freelance during the hours of your
scheduled employment, otherwise you get
into uh
the very dangerous territory and you
open yourself up to some liability.
And speaking of liability,
um I wanted to uh
uh talk about one legal issue that's
very important and that's
indemnification.
So, I'm not a lawyer,
um
but I can tell you that in any of your
contracts, you want to have what's
called an indemnification clause.
And this basically says that
if the code you write is then used by
the company and then causes some sort of
damage,
then your liability is limited and
whoever is being damaged can't sue you.
They can only sue the company.
And this is called an indemnification
clause.
And it's just it's very important that
you have that.
Because it limits your risk.
So,
going back to the process of landing a
job a little bit because we segued into
legal issues that are very important as
well. It's a very It's It's It's a very
good tip because I can understand that
you can be ruined if you get sued. But I
want to talk more about that process of
you're in touch with a customer. For
example,
do you do some free work? You already
mentioned it a little bit if you follow
up seven times and you give them a tip,
basically you're doing free work for
them and you want to
occur trustful and be helpful, but also
you don't want to be stringed along and
then after months of you giving them
free tips, they're like, "Yeah, I know
we're going to go with someone else." So
All right. I I I totally understand the
question.
Yeah, I've been through this exact issue
many times.
So
in essence, you want to do a little bit
of free work at the very beginning.
You know, if you come across if someone
asks you a basic question and then you
say, "Hey, I'm not going to do free work
for you." You know, then you know, you
you risk coming across as kind of a jerk
because in the beginning
it's really like an interview process.
So, you want to be consultative and give
them value and get them, you know, more
or less addicted to the value that you
provide. But
you know, once you get in the door with,
you know, a few back and forth exchanges
where you're actually delivering value
and they're not just testing the limits
of your knowledge, but you're actually
giving them insight, then the language
or the phrase that I like to use is
we're encroaching upon the limits of
non-billable time.
I'd love to assist you in this matter.
Here's my contract. Let's get it signed
and then we can continue.
Yeah, so you don't say no immediately.
You're just saying you're reaching the
end of where I want to go for free.
Well, I I I I prefer to talk about it as
non-billable time.
Non-billable, yeah, but that's basically
a euphemism for
Yeah,
but but it's a little bit more polite
and it's a little bit more delicate.
maybe a little bit more professional. I
totally get that.
So, is is upselling a thing? You're
working for a customer maybe a few hours
a week or you're doing a project but you
think there might be something bigger?
Is this something you do and how do you
go about it?
Uh it's something that I do and it's
something that I do once I've developed
some trust with the client. So, once I
have delivered results and they have
paid me and my invoices are finalized
and the money is finalized and the
transfer,
then
and we've repeated this process a couple
times and I can say,
you know, hey, you know, you know, you
can refer them to someone else if you
want to if you want and then you know,
you maybe you have a commission
relationship with that person
or you say, you know, I could do this
and this and this for you.
It's totally a thing and it's a great
idea, but you want to do that uh once
you've developed more trust. And this
this consulting freelancing process is
really all about trust and developing a
level of trust. And you need to build up
to a certain level of trust in order to
get them to bring you on.
And then once you deliver results, then
it will increase the level of trust. And
I'd like to segue into a point here
um about that.
So, a lot of people have, you know, very
strong skills and there's a lot of value
that they could provide companies, but
um the way it works is that almost every
freelance developer I know
uh gets their foot in the door through
client that's having a very specific
problem
with a very specific
kind of technology.
For example, I'm just going to use this
as a for instance, let's say the client
is building a react application
and they're blocked somewhere and they
need to bring on a freelancer.
By being very very strong at react, you
increase the level of trust you have for
the client which enables you to then
pivot into doing other kinds of
freelance work for them such as not
through react.
You know, a lot of people
you know, you know, you see an ad,
they're looking for let's say a Java
developer.
And you see the problem you can you see,
you know what? I know how to solve this,
but I would not use Java, I would use
Ruby.
And you know, nine times out of 10
that's not going to work. The client has
their mind made up. They want someone
with a very specific niche skill set.
And then once you
blow them away and deliver good results
and value for them
through you know, your work
then what happens is your level of trust
elevates.
And then you could start making
recommendations. Oh, I want to solve
this problem, but I want to use a
different technology and you tend to be
able to get away with that a lot more
because you have shown excellence in a
very specific niche technical skill.
So
my advice is have a few things that you
are very very strong at to use to get
your foot in the door cuz a lot of
clients they really want an expert with
a specific technology. And I completely
agree that it that's that's kind of a
silly way of thinking perhaps and it's
possible that they could do it a lot
better just using the technology that
you know best.
Okay, but in order to build trust, just
the due to the dynamics, the social
dynamics of the situation, what they
really want is an expert in a specific
technology.
And once you have demonstrated your
expertise in that specific niche
technology,
then you can pivot and do things for
them using other technologies, using
other types of solution paradigms, if
you will.
But
you it's people really want to see
someone who will just knock their socks
off with a specific technology.
Yeah, clear. So, you can only do
upselling once you've gained trust and
once you've sold them the thing that
they have a need for. You don't
immediately go, like you said, maybe
being a jerk saying, "Oh, you're wrong
and you should use this." First, you
just go with it, build trust, and only
then you offer ideas or other services
that you might be able to provide.
Exactly. And it's just it's it's really
annoying that that's how the dynamics of
the freelancing market are,
but I've just seen it time and time
again. The way to get your foot in with
a client who might want you to be,
you know, like a generalist CTO type for
them,
is to be able to deliver excellence
using the technology that that they have
in mind. Maybe there's a logic to it and
I just I haven't figured it out, but I
can tell you that I've seen time and
time again client posts an ad, they they
use a buzzword, they may not know what
the buzzword means, but they won't move
forward until you demonstrate confidence
with the buzzword that they have in
mind. It's just
And once And once you're there, you
increase trust and you increase your
ability to lead them elsewhere.
And this happens in regular companies,
in regular employment situations as
well, I think, where manager has set his
heart on getting, I don't know, React or
node and then even as full time employee
it's sometimes hard to convince your
manager that no they actually want
something else or customer even if
you're employed by a company you have a
customer that might want something. So
the general strategy of
doing what they want and only then
showing expertise after you've built
trust I don't think it's even that
specific to freelancing situation this
happens in in regular employment
situations also I think.
Do you agree?
Yeah that's been my experience as well.
Yeah absolutely. But I just I see I just
see time and time again people who apply
to ads saying you know I am awesome you
know do it my way.
You you got to you got there's a thing
in um
in sales called pacing and leading.
What what does that mean facing and
leading?
Sure. So
it means that when you are dealing with
a new prospect or group you want to
match the cadence and rhythm of their
communication
before you suggest elsewhere. So if
someone is if they're using react you
want to go in with react
get on pace with react and then you can
lead them elsewhere. Maybe you want to
take them to Scala or closure or you
know whatever tool that you find to be
elixir maybe whatever. I'm not going to
get into a language war here.
But the idea is to match them exactly
where they are and follow along at the
same pace before you lead them
elsewhere.
Clear. Let's talk about finance. This is
a topic that's sometimes hard for people
to talk about. So you don't have to
share your hourly rate but I'm
interested do you share do you charge an
hourly rate or do you charge customers
for a finished project?
In the rare event that a customer knows
exactly what they're looking for, and
it's specified in great detail, and it's
not likely to change through building.
Like for example,
let's say they've already built a
prototype, and they've solved all the
issues with the V1, and they're ready to
build a V2,
then I'm open to a fixed price.
But unless there is an exact
specification that's very clear with a
very clear set of deliverables that can
be answered in a is this fulfilled yes
or no type of way,
I don't like doing a fixed price. I'd
like doing um
Right now I charge an hourly rate, and I
also charge a markup on top of any
subcontractors I use. So in uh
construction, this is referred to as
time and materials. So this is the kind
of model that general contractors will
use when say building a house.
They uh they charge a rate for their
time, and then they charge for any
materials like for example web hosting
fees, or a subcontractor,
or a certain software as a service
subscription that helps push things
forward.
Uh I What I charge is I charge an hourly
rate for my time. I build it in quarter
hour increments, and then I charge a
markup um for
any you know materials used. And
uh just in terms of my rate, right now I
charge $185 an hour,
and I do a markup of anywhere from 10 to
30%
for uh materials used.
Do you regularly work with sub-
subcontractors, or is that only if you
need specific skills that you don't have
yourself?
I regularly work with subcontractors,
yeah.
If uh if I've built a lot of trust with
the client, then they'll usually want to
put me on multiple projects. And it's
just sort of a law of development,
software development, that you really
can't do any good quality-focused work
if you're working on more than one
project at a time.
I think most software engineering
management books will will mention this.
And you really want to keep developers
focused on one project at a time.
So, if I'm in a code base, and then I I
really only want to be in one code base
at a time because I need to build up
a good knowledge of the code base in my
memory and in in my short-term memory,
and I need to be able to
understand where everything is in order
to be efficient. I need to keep a mental
model of it. And when you're dealing
with multiple code bases simultaneously,
just
the results suffer tremendously. So, I
I deal with subcontractors very
frequently nowadays.
You just mentioned your hourly rate. How
did you calculate that? If if I want to
charge an an amount, how do I know what
to charge? Is it just what the customer
needs to pay, or is there a formula I
can use?
Yeah, absolutely. So, right now it's the
formula for me is supply and demand. If
I you know, if I need work, I will you
know, lower my rate, but if I am getting
swamped with requests for work, then I
will incrementally increase my rate. And
but let's talk about finding a baseline
for your rate.
Yeah. Yeah, no, that sounds good, the
baseline, because I understand there's
demand, but also how do you go about a
baseline? Tell me.
Sh- Sure. So, you take your annual
salary and you divide it by 2,000. And
that's your baseline hourly rate.
Okay, so what you're saying is 2,000
hours is more or less
Well, let's just I'll use round numbers
for the sake of discussion.
Let's say that your salary is 100,000 a
year in whatever local currency.
Then you divide it by 2,000 and then you
get 50 and that's your hourly rate.
So, that effectively
is the formula for annualizing
what your salary would be. And that's
that's where you want to put the floor
of your hourly rate.
Now, in practice, you want to set that
higher for a number of reasons. One is
because if you're freelancing, you're
not getting all the benefits of
employment. And the next is you don't
have the stability because when you're
freelancing, you have to be hunting for
work and there're going to be gaps in
your you're not going to be working for
40 hours a week necessarily.
And you know, you need to make up for
that.
But just as a floor, as a baseline, you
take your your what your what your
annual salary would be on the market and
then you divide it by 2,000. But I'll
tell you this,
in practice, if you take your consulting
salary, your freelancing salary, and
then
you try to get an employment position,
you'll find that you're going to be if
you've are any good at sales, you're
going to find that
you're going to be making a much higher
effective rate for your time as a
freelancer.
So,
for just as for example, some years ago,
I was charging $85 an hour as a
freelancer and if I were employed full
time, that would translate to $160,000
a year,
but I found that I was struggling to get
employment with jobs at an $80,000 a
year salary. So,
you you're as a freelancer, you can make
a higher effective hourly rate for your
time,
but you know,
there's the the of finding work
consistently. But also the bar to entry
is lower. For example, as a freelancer,
uh I find that you're going to be
subjected to whiteboarding interviews a
lot less often.
You're not going to get quizzed on
algorithms.
It's just a matter of
do you know the specific niche
technology that the company is looking
for at this time? Do you have
experience? Have you done it before?
And you know, can can you deliver
results?
So, they're you're they're not going to
there's going to be less, you know,
hazing or abuse through these whiteboard
quizzes and these take-home assignments.
Though occasionally I I I do see
take-home assignments for freelancing
interviews, but I it's a much rarer to
see the whiteboard algorithm questions.
So, are there other things you need to
take into account because the formula's
really nice taking your
annual income as a baseline, but of
course you have other expenses if you're
a freelancer. Maybe you need insurance,
you need unemployment insurance, you
have to do savings for a pension, all
these type of things. Does that all come
out of that hourly rate you just
described or are there extra things you
need to do, the extra costs?
Yeah, absolutely. I mean, like I said,
as a rule of thumb, that's just the
baseline. That's the floor. And you want
to yeah, ideally
uh double it. I but the truth is in
freelancing you want to charge as much
as possible. You want to charge the rate
that the market will bear.
So, if you know, a company uh is willing
to pay you at a high rate, then you
know, then you want to charge a higher
rate because you're right, you do have
to take care of insurance, you have to
take care of pension, you have to take
care of
uh meals. A lot of companies you know,
give catered food for their employees
nowadays. And you also have to make up
for the inconsistency in work cuz work
comes when it when it rains it pours is
the is an expression and it's
extremely true with freelancing. It's
it's a bit like, you know, dating in
that way. You know, when when you're
desperate you give off these signals and
just subconsciously
it uh repels people. And the same thing
is true when applying for work. So, yes,
you definitely want to charge higher
than the baseline minimum, but just as a
heuristic for example, if you're
employed and you're looking for side
work you can just take your salary and
divide it by 2,000 to find your hourly
rate. So, if you're already employed
full-time and you're looking for some
side side income to supplement your
income, then uh just take your annual
salary and divide by 2,000.
Uh but you really want to increase it
from there.
I just have to say that um
there's a certain psychological pressure
that companies don't want to pay a
certain hourly rate above a certain
hourly rate.
For example, with PHP development uh you
know, there where there's a huge market
cuz it's one of the most it's the most
common language for web development. Now
yeah, there are PHP developers available
for $5 an hour. There are PHP developers
that are available for $400 an hour.
Now, the $400 an hour uh PHP developers,
you know, you really in order to get to
that level you really need to have
written a framework or, you know,
several books, given lots of talks and
you know, have, you know, maybe 10,000
plus followers on Twitter. Like just I
don't know if those are exact numbers,
but just as a rule of thumb you need to
be like a well-known persona in the
industry in order to
consistently get away with charging
those rates.
But a lot of companies will have a
psychological aversion
to
um
a super high hourly rate.
And even if you're an efficient
developer
um who could get more done in 1 hour
that someone at half your rate would
take in 5 hours, even if that's the
case,
just psychologically people aren't going
to go for it.
Um and that's an issue. And
uh there are various ways around this,
you know, and it really depends on
uh how you know, how you feel morally.
So what some people do is they charge
you know, they bill out at a lower
hourly rate, but then they inflate their
hours.
Uh I don't suggest doing this because
you know, one, the easiest way to
you know, not have to remember anything
is just tell the truth.
And also, there's a question of
integrity.
Um
but I I've seen very frequently in the
industry, I talk to freelancers all the
time and I see consistently that they
will admit that when dealing with
companies that don't want to pay a high
hourly rate, they advertise at a low
hourly rate and they just inflate their
hours.
Um
I'm not here to pass a moral judgment. I
can say I personally don't want to work
with anyone who inflates their hours,
but I can tell you that it happens all
the time.
So,
uh you know,
uh the other, you know, side of the coin
is just charge your
rate even if it's low, get the work done
efficiently,
and then just move on and find new
business. And just be secure in the fact
that you have a baseline of clients who
are going to be providing you income,
and that will enable you to charge a
higher rate with uh
new prospects.
So, you can sort of
low and build up from there.
Yeah, in in the lingo of business, it's
called a BATNA or a Batna,
which is a best alternative to no
agreement. In other words, it
strengthens your ability to walk away
from a deal,
which means a higher price.
Those are great tips.
I wanted to talk about one final topic
before we before we end the episode, and
that's work-life balance. Because even
if you have a regular employment, it can
be challenging to not check your email
at night or not to do some work or take
some work home or have a late-night
meeting. How do you manage that if
you're freelancer? How do you How do you
do that personally? What do you think is
the best way? Do you try to stick to
office hours or do you work evenings and
chill in the afternoon?
You know, I'm I'm laughing cuz I can
tell you for a fact that I haven't fully
cracked this nut. I haven't fully found
the true
work-life balance
uh path path.
And I can tell you that personally I'm a
I'm a very ambitious person, so
I'm okay with trading a work-life
balance to have more agency
uh in my career.
Uh ultimately. Um but
uh I can I can definitely provide some
tips here and and things that I've
learned. So, for example,
you know, when you are working as an
employee in an office, you're going to
have a peer group and sort of a built-in
friend group. A lot of people socialize
and make friendships with the people
they work with. I mean,
often times you spend more time
of your life with the people who you're
in office with than you do say with your
family or significant other.
So, you don't have when you're
freelancing, you don't necessarily have
that built-in social environment. So,
you know, for me, I've had to find ways
of making friendships outside of
freelancing and
uh for me that's been one thing I've
done a lot is meet-up groups. So, not
just meet-up related to tech and which
is by the way a great way to find
clients,
but
and a lot easier to get accepted to give
a talk at a meet-up than it is to get
accepted to give a talk at a big
conference and it's a great marketing
technique. And plenty of companies and
people with the authority to influence
hiring decisions at companies including
freelancer hiring will attend these
meet-ups. And it's much easier to get
your foot in the door and experience
giving talks at meet-ups. And one more
thing I want to say is there's this myth
that in order to give talks at
conferences and meet-ups, you have to
just be solicited. People have to reach
out and ask you to do that. It's not the
case. I can tell you for a fact that if
you just make a list of meet-ups
and you write to them and say,
"Hey, I'm an expert in this topic. I'd
love to give a talk about it at the next
meet-up."
Uh a lot of people will say, "Yes, that
would be awesome." meetup.com is a great
resource for that.
Um there are a lot of sports clubs such
as everything from bowling leagues to
softball
or is a good way to meet people. There
are a lot of bars
where
it's they have if a bar has Wi-Fi, you
could probably go with a book or a
laptop and meet people. And there are
you know, it's becomes acceptable in a
lot of places if the bar has Wi-Fi, it's
implied that there's going to be certain
people on their laptop. You can work
from a bar or a coffee shop, and that
can be a great way to meet people. And,
you know,
regularly do that? Do you work from bars
and coffee shops, or do you work at the
customer's office, or do you work from
home?
Oh, yeah. I I um
I I hate going on-site to a customer
office. I really really try to avoid
that whenever possible because
they're just increased costs. Like,
first off, you don't get paid for the
commute time.
So, that time definitely adds up. Second
is that as a freelancer, you know,
there's there's generally a higher
standard for dress when you have to go
into the office. You know, that if
you're charging a high hourly rate,
people want to see you in, you know, I
at least you know, business casual or
fancier dress. And then that creates
costs cuz, you know, then you have dry
cleaning expenses.
And you know, and then it just it's a
lot more effort to have to
get all groomed up every day going
on-site, and I also find that I get less
work done when I'm on-site. But, you
know, of course, you want to face time
with clients is very valuable, and you
want to build that relationship wherever
possible, but I found that, you know,
clients enjoy the face time more when
you take them out of the office. Like, a
really good way to keep a client who
sends you a lot of business is to take,
you know,
maybe 5% of the income that you make
from them, and just invest that in
treating them to really nice dinners,
nice seats at a sporting event, and
whatever they might be interested in.
So, that that's just a a miscellaneous
note.
And in terms of, you know,
balancing your schedule,
what I recommend is just being
communicative with a client about your
hours, so they aren't surprised. And so
they know when they can get a hold of
you and when they can't. And be very
careful about starting a pattern where
the client feels comfortable calling you
at 10:00 p.m. or on the weekend, because
once you start that, they're not going
to want to give that up.
So, it's very important to enforce a
boundary on that from the beginning if
that's something that's important to
you.
But that might contrast a little bit
with the trust you're building or the
relationship you have in the beginning
because you said you have to sort of
follow their pace. So, if this is a
thing they do, then you your your advice
still is to keep your own
protect your own way of doing it and
maybe then not have a customer.
It's right. It's I mean, what Well,
yeah. Okay, so now I'm hemming and
hawing a little bit. Um
But
But I you know, I will say you
definitely want to be on board with
whatever technology that they want to
use in the beginning.
I've also found that if if a client is
consistently calling you on the weekend,
you know, it's just they're not a good
client cuz these kinds of clients
tend to be very costly in terms of
emotional stress.
Just like, you know, the if you have a
job where you're they're working you
like a dog for 60 hours, 70 hours, 80
hours a week consistently,
it's probably not going to be the best
work environment.
Clients who, you know, want you on the
weekend to be working all the time,
I just I
I'm thinking back through my years and
years of experience and it's almost
never ended well. I mean, the only time
that kind of thing I think has worked is
when the client is also a developer and
they're working side by side with you
during the weekend.
But if it's a client who's just barking
orders at you during the weekend,
I found that those clients tend to be
bad news. Just the stress that they
cause is not worth
the value, you know? And then they get
surprised when you send them a bill for
all the hours that they have run up. So
it's very important to set expectations
and manage expectations there. And I'm
on my journey, too. I haven't fully
perfected this balance. I've been at it
I've been freelancing since
well, like officially since 2007, you
know, even before that I guess since
2003. So I've been at it a while and I
haven't fully perfected this. I mean,
it's it's an art as well. I mean, there
are some formulas. There is that
heuristic of the divide by 2000 to get
the very baseline, but
there's always room for growth, you
know?
But I I I found that clients who are
very demanding at nights and weekends,
you know, those are the clients that are
going to give you a hard time about
paying your invoice. So you want to pace
and lead, but if a client is
constantly hammering you on the weekends
and
pestering you constantly, these kind of
difficult clients are going to be the
ones who you will see problems when you
send them an invoice. I've seen this
repeatedly.
So be very careful
And it's a bad sign. If they don't have
their stuff in order, they need to call
you in the weekend, other stuff will be
bad, also.
Oh, yeah, absolutely. It's it's a red
flag. And be very careful when you see
red flags from clients, cuz although
there can be some exceptions,
you should to an extent trust your
instincts, especially if you've been
freelancing for a while. But I will say
that if you're just a developer and you
haven't had any experience in sales,
maybe don't trust your instincts. And
and and and be open to
sort of a softer,
less precise, more
uh
rhythmic approach to to sales. So, don't
think that clients are just trying to
abuse you and get work for free.
Remember that if they're asking you
specific technical questions,
they're not necessarily just trying to
get your work for free cuz they may not
even be able to implement. They just
want to see what you know and see if you
admit when you don't know things. So,
just remember that early in the process,
it can just be an interview just as much
as anything else. And it's not like
they're trying to squeeze
work out of you for free necessarily.
Oh, one more thing that I want to
mention.
When you're a freelancer, it's less an
employer-employee relationship and more
of a business-to-business relationship.
Therefore,
it can be totally appropriate to ask the
client for references.
Just as an employer might ask you for
references before they hire you,
if you're a freelancer,
you can definitely
offer an exchange of references with a
client.
It both, you know, puts you in
a more of a power position socially by
checking them just as they check you.
And that can help with the sales
process. But,
it will also help you avoid some bad
clients.
Yeah, that's a great tip where you ask
other freelancers what their
experiences with the customer have been.
Exactly.
Great.
Or fellow freelancers.
Thanks a lot. That was really great.
Lots to process. I just want to ask you
one more question and that's where can
we follow you? Of course, we've
mentioned your book. We will put a link
to your book in the show notes, but are
there other places where we can follow
you and learn more about these
freelancing tips?
Sure. So, I have a website called Code
for Cash. It's a software as a service,
and what we do is we scour the internet
for
uh freelance job leads.
And so, we're constantly monitoring
over 50 different job boards looking for
contract opportunities both on-site and
remote.
Uh 1099 or contract base versus
full-time employee.
And we have a human intelligence team
that takes all these
data that we ingest and adds metadata to
make the filtering process better. And
then you can we have a sophisticated uh
keyword positive keyword, negative
keyword matching system, and then we
send real-time alerts in Slack. So,
if you've been freelancing for a while,
you'll notice that what you'll do is
when you're looking for work, you'll
occasionally browse various markets.
You know, you may even have an RSS
reader set up, but we just take that to
the next level. So, if you're interested
in about the lead gen system for
freelancers, check out Code for Cash,
and I'll give Felina a
a link to that.
Yeah, we'll make sure that that is in
the show notes as well. Well, thanks
again for being on the show. It was
great.
Oh, thank you. It's been a pleasure to
be here. And you know, part of me is
sorry that it's ending.
Thanks.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine.
For more about the podcast, including
other episodes, visit our website at
SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5.
Thanks for listening.